Guide to the Benjamin Iceland Papers ALBA.054
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Benjamin Iceland Papers
1937-1996
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Iceland, Benjamin, 1910-1990
ALBA.054
2 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
Ben Iceland (1910-1990) fought with the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in the Spanish Civil War. In civilian life he found work as a social worker, farmer and, finally, as a high-school teacher of Latin. Iceland was an active member of the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB) and edited VALB’s newsletter, the Volunteer, for eight years. This collection contains correspondence written while Iceland was in Spain and memoirs of his participation in the Spanish Civil War. It also contains correspondence and subject files, most from the 1980s, related to VALB and the Volunteer.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains Iceland's letters from Spain to Claire Brown Iceland, and several chapter-length typescript accounts of his Spanish Civil War experiences. Much of the collection consists of correspondence, articles, clippings, VALB reports and memos, and other materials related to Iceland's tenure as editor. The last box of the collection houses Iceland's unpublished translation of Virgil's Aeneid.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Separated Materials
Photographs from the Ben Iceland Collection have been transferred to the Non-Print section of the ALBA collection in the Tamiment Library.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
ALBA collections at the Tamiment Library.
Arrangement
This collection has been organized into 3 series:
The materials are arranged alphabetically within each series.
Missing Title
Series I: Spanish Civil War, 1977-1990
Series II: Correspondence, 1976-1996
Series III: Subject Files, 1937-1940
The materials are arranged alphabetically within each series. This collection has been organized into 3 series:
Historical/Biographical Note
Ben Iceland (1910-1990), son of the Yiddish poet Rueben Iceland, was born on New York’s Lower East Side and raised in the Bronx. Iceland graduated from New York University in 1933 with a degree in classics. Upon graduation he held a series of makeshift jobs, everything from shoveling snow to working as a theater usher, until taking a position in 1934 with New York City’s Home Relief Bureau, the forerunner of the Welfare Department. Once he landed a steady job, Iceland married Claire Brown, a union organizer.
In 1937, Iceland, against the wishes of his wife and unbeknownst to his mother, joined the International Brigades. During the Spanish Civil War he was a machine-gunner with the Czech and John Brown anti-aircraft batteries, and he was among the last American volunteers to leave Spain. Upon his return from Spain, Iceland, a member of the Communist Party from the mid-1930s, rejoined the city’s Welfare Department. When his membership in the Communist Party was exposed, however, he lost his job. By the early 1940s Iceland’s marriage had ended. When World War II broke out, Iceland joined the United States Army, and spent the war years on duty in California. After the war Iceland took a job helping displaced European Jews find work and housing, and he worked briefly as a union organizer. Finding himself increasingly under investigation by the FBI, Iceland bought a farm outside Albany, and took up farming near Frank “Ski” Buturla, a friend from the Spanish Civil War. In 1962, after having obtained a graduate degree, Iceland moved to New Jersey and taught Latin in a local high school until he retired in 1976. Iceland had by this time remarried. His second wife, Marianne, was a native of Vienna.
Iceland was an active member of the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB). In 1982 Manny Harriman, then retiring as editor of the Volunteer, VALB’s newsletter, tapped Iceland to become the next editor thus moving editorial functions of the Volunteer from the West Coast to the East. Changing the location of the Volunteer's editorial board was only one of many VALB controversies over which Iceland would preside as editor. Iceland served as editor of the Volunteer from 1982 until shortly before his death in 1990.
Provenance
The Ben Iceland Collection was donated to the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives by Marianne Iceland in 1995. This collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of ALBA collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University.
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Personal narratives.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |v Biography.; Drafts (documents); Articles.; Personal papers.; Correspondence.; Translations (documents); Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; Weissman, Irving, 1905-; Wolff, Milton.; Schutt, Wilhelm (Willi); Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives; Berch, Victor A.; Bessie, Alvah Cecil, 1904-1985; Geiser, Carl; Nelson, Steve, 1903-1993
- Series I: Spanish Civil War Era, 1937-1940
  Scope and Content Note
  This series consists of correspondence, mostly from Ben Iceland to his wife, Claire Brown Iceland; Iceland’s English-Spanish grammar book; photocopies of documents relating to Iceland’s time in Spain; and photocopied typescripts of Iceland’s memoirs of the Spanish Civil War.
  - Biographical, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Iceland, Ben to Claire Brown Iceland, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Iceland, Ben to Claire Brown Iceland, March-July 1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Iceland, Ben to Claire Brown Iceland, August, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Iceland, Ben to Claire Brown Iceland, September-October 1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Iceland, Ben to Rueben (Rubin) Iceland, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Lossowski, Vincent et al: “The Gypsy’s Curse”, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Postcard: photograph of last Americans leaving Spain, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Publication: “English-Spanish Grammar”, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Repatriation: List, December 1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Sailing Announcement, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Writings: “Alamansa”, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Writings: “Anniversary”, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Writings: “The Big Retreat”, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Writings: “Early Days in Spain”, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Writings: “Last Months in Spain”, Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Writings: “Teruel”, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Writings: “A Train is Bombed”, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1976-1996
  The bulk of the correspondence (1982-1990) is from fellow veterans of the Spanish Civil War, and is related to Iceland’s tenure as editor of the Volunteer. Many letters expand on controversies within VALB, or comment on articles and reviews published in the Volunteer. Subjects include contemporary issues such as the war in Nicaragua and proliferation of nuclear arms; the selection of material for the anthology, Our Fight, edited by Alvah Bessie and Albert Prago; as well as subjects related to the Spanish Civil War. Communism and Socialism were perennial sources of debate. Many letters include reminiscences of the war in Spain.
  The correspondence includes letters from more than fifty different persons; Victor Berch, Alvah Bessie, Irving Weissman and Milton Wolff are among the more prolific correspondents. A 1990 letter from Carl Geiser provides a lengthy description of his trip to Cuba. Notable, too, is the correspondence from Wilhelm “Willi” Schutt, a 1929 German immigrant to New York City who fought with the Lincoln Battalion in Spain. Schutt, denied entry to the United States after the Spanish Civil War, lived in England during World War II. After the war he moved to East Germany where he lived until his death.
  - Cards, Undated, 1977-1983 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - General, Undated, 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - General, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - General, 1983-1989 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - General, 1990-1996 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Amery, Alfred, Undated, 1983-1990 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Bailey, Bill, 1982-1986 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Bender, Ed, 1983; 1986 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Berch, Victor, Undated, 1976-1990 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Bessie, Alvah and Sylviane, Undated, 1981-1987 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Carroll, Peter, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Chase, Homer, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Cogswell, Theodore, Undated, 1980-1987 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Colodny, Robert, 1972; 1987 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Colow, Maury, 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Doyle, Joe, Undated, 1982-1996 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Felsen, Milton, 1982-1990 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Fishman, Moe, Undated, 1977-1986 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Gandall, William (Bill), Undated, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Gerlach, John, Undated, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Geiser, Carl, 1981-1990 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Goldring, Benjamin, 1979-1983 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Grunblatt, Jacques, M.D., 1981-1990 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Harriman, Manny, Undated, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Heisler, Gus, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Hornstein, Claire Brown Iceland Hartford, 1976-1984 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Kaye, George, Undated, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Kaufman, Sidney, Undated, 1982-1986 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Landis, Arthur H., Undated, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Landing, Arthur Isaac, 1978-1989 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Levenson, Leonard, 1977-1988 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Lossowski, Vincent, 1978-1984 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - MacLeod, Don, 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Martin, Fredicka, 1978; 1982 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Nusser, Charles, Undated, 1982-1986 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Nelson, Steve, Undated, 1976-1987 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Osheroff, Abe, Undated, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Postek, Stanley, Undated, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Parker, Max and Mary, Undated, 1983; 1989 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Pike, William, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Prago, Albert, Undated, 1982-1989 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Reed, Robert, 1982-1983, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Rosenberg, Leo, Undated, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Rosner, Hyman, Undated, 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Ross, Adolf, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Schuetrum, Walter, 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Schutt, Wilhelm (Willi), 1982 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Smorodin, Abe, Undated, 1985-1991 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Stamm, Morris, 1977-1983 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Steck, Robert, Undated, 1980-1984 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Tivin, Isadore (Izzy), 1982 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Watt, George, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Weissman, Irving, Undated, 1978-1982 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Wellman, Saul, Undated, 1977-1986 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Wisse, Ruth, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Wolff, Milton, Undated, 1982-1987 (Box 1, Folder 74)
- Series III: Subject Files, 1977-1990
  Most of the material in the subject files consists of documents related to VALB, on both the national and regional level, and the Volunteer. Correspondence, publicity material and documents about events commemorating the 50th anniversary of the Spanish Civil War are also well represented. Iceland’s full-length translation of Virgil’s Aeneid is included in the subject files.
  - Abraham Lincoln Brigade: Clippings, Undated, 1982-1985 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Abraham Lincoln Brigade: Film Project, 1982-1984 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Abraham Lincoln Brigade: Memorial Scholarship, CUNY, Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Abraham Lincoln Brigade: Monument, Barcelona, Undated, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Abraham Lincoln Brigade: Veterans’ Rights, Legislation, 1978; 1981 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, Undated, 1978-1983 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Collins, Len, Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Dreams and Nightmares (film), Undated, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Falcon, Lydia, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Good Fight (film), Undated, 1984-1987 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Hemingway, Ernest: “Some Personal Impressions of…” by William Pike, Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - International Brigade Association, Undated, 1984-1989 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - MacLeod, Don: “Voices from the Underdogs”, Undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Nicaragua, Undated, 1985-1987 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Pappo, Marice: Sullivanian Therapy, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Prago, Albert: “The USSR and Aid to the Spanish Republic”, Undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Spain: Santiago Carillo and the Yale Strike, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Spain: Communist Party, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Spain: Democracy, 1982-1984 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Spanish Civil War: 35th Anglo-American Battery, Undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Spanish Civil War: 35th Anglo-American Battery, Undated, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Spanish Civil War: “Fifty Years Later: Some Thoughts on…” by Irving Weissman, Undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Spanish Civil War: Jewish Volunteers, Undated, 1984-1990 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Spanish Civil War: Letters, excerpts, Undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Spanish Civil War: “Walter (1897-1947) a Soldier in Spain”, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Spanish Civil War Veterans Committee: USSR, Undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB): 44th Anniversary, Undated, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB): 50th Anniversary, Correspondence, 1985-1987 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB): 50th Anniversary, Events, Undated, 1985-1987 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB): 50th Anniversary, Program at Drew University, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB): Bay Post, Undated, 1981-1986 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB): Detroit, Scholarship Fund Benefit, Undated, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB): Los Angeles Post, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB): National, Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB): National, 1973-1979 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB): National, 1980-1987 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB): National, 1990-1994 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB): New York Post, Undated, 1977-1992 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB): Reprints, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB): Seattle, Undated, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB): Spanish Civil War, Prisoner Historical Commission, Undated, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB): Spanish Civil War Historical Commission, Undated, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Volunteer: Articles, Undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Volunteer: Drawing, Undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Volunteer: Iceland, Ben, “Last Days in Spain”, Undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Volunteer: Levenson, Leonard, Undated, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Volunteer: Miscellaneous, Undated, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Volunteer: Weissman, Irving, Notes, Undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Weissman, Irving: “Fifty Years Later: Some Thoughts on the Spanish Civil War”, Undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - World War II: World Assembly to Commemorate Jewish Resistance, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - World War II: “Yank—The Story of the War”, Undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Writings: The Aeneid of Virgil, Translation (Books I-VI), Undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Writings: The Aeneid of Virgil, Translation (Books VII-XII), Undated (Box 3, Folder 20)